<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><transcript><prologue></prologue><scene id="1" in="00:00:01.04" out="00:00:12.28">&lt;speaker&gt; Monique Shore &lt;/speaker&gt;
Monique | Alright, so you were saying that that one [pointing] was the post office. That’s the first Assembly of God Church in this area. Alright.</scene><scene id="2" in="00:00:12.29" out="00:00:15.24">&lt;speaker&gt; Glen Bell &lt;/speaker&gt;
Glenn | And that’s my mother-in-law’s writing.</scene><scene id="3" in="00:00:15.25" out="00:00:25.17">Monique | Okay.  Moved from Gilman. Oh, so they physically moved the building. 
Glenn | Yeah and built the, this church out of it.
Monique | But this is the building as it stood in Gilman.</scene><scene id="4" in="00:00:25.18" out="00:00:26.09">&lt;speaker&gt; Margaret Stone &lt;/speaker&gt;
Margaret | Yes.</scene><scene id="5" in="00:00:26.10" out="00:00:41.11">Glenn | Yes. It’s the post office. Okay. Alright. And on the window you can see printed that Edward B Wright Evangelist. 
Monique | Old time revival service every night. There you go. Yeah.</scene><scene id="6" in="00:00:41.12" out="00:00:58.24">Glenn | And that was my father-in-law. 
Monique | Okay
Glenn | Okay. Then they moved that to Grinnell and built this little white church.
Monique | Okay. Out of this as their frame-work. 
Glenn | Uh-huh.</scene><scene id="7" in="00:00:58.25" out="00:01:17.19">Monique | Huh. So they first started meeting in Gilman. 
Glenn | He was holding Evangelistic meetings in Gilman. 
Monique | Because he was holding Evangelistic meetings at Gilman, okay. 
Glenn | It wasn’t charted yet. Assembly of God.</scene><scene id="8" in="00:01:17.20" out="00:01:47.25">Monique | And what was his name?
Glenn | Edward B. Wright.
Monique | Wright, w-r-i-g-h-t?
Glenn | Right.</scene><scene id="9" in="00:01:47.26" out="00:02:21.08">[pause]
Monique | So do you happen to know, is this Edward B. Wright in this picture?
Glenn | Yes, that’s George Wright, I mean, George Driscoll and Edward Wright. They were partners, in house-moving</scene><scene id="10" in="00:02:21.09" out="00:02:29.27">Monique | But Edward was also the preacher?
Glenn | He was the Evangelist. 
Margaret | Yes.
Monique | He was the Evangelist and a house-mover? 
Glenn | Yes.</scene><scene id="11" in="00:02:29.28" out="00:02:51.08">Monique | Alright. [laughs] So there are three gentlemen in this picture. Do you happen to know which one is which? 
Glenn | Oh, I didn’t see the one in the middle. [laughs] This is my father-in-law, here [pointing] 
Margaret | Far right.
Glenn | Far right.</scene><scene id="12" in="00:02:51.09" out="00:03:13.21">Monique | And that's Edward-
Margaret | Edward B. Wright.
Glenn | Yes.
Monique | Okay.  
Glenn | And the one on the other side is, I’m thinking it's George Driscoll. I don’t know who the one in the middle is.</scene><scene id="13" in="00:03:13.22" out="00:03:29.05">Monique | Okay
Glenn | I’m thinking probably one of Ed’s boys. 
Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | Could have been Elmer.  Or George-
Margaret | Maybe George has a boy too.
Glenn | Well he did but he didn't help.</scene><scene id="14" in="00:03:29.06" out="00:03:58.17">Monique | So do you have any idea when this picture would have been taken?
Glenn | Okay. I have an idea. Now the church was incorporated, she’s got all that information, in ’34. But before this church was moved, they held, they rented a storefront uptown and had meetings. They met at a store front.</scene><scene id="15" in="00:03:58.18" out="00:04:11.16">Monique | Here in Grinnell?
Glenn | Here in the early thirties. Yeah. Along where Rutkins is. Right in—
Monique | So you’re thinking they probably moved the building from Gilman in the early thirties?
Glenn | Yeah. Yeah.</scene><scene id="16" in="00:04:11.17" out="00:04:26.10">Monique | Okay. Alright. Very good. Let’s see. I’m going to get—
Glenn | But let me finish my little story there. 
Monique | Okay.</scene><scene id="17" in="00:04:26.11" out="00:04:49.27">Glenn | They had a store front rented and they met there and had Evangelist come in and hold services. They didn’t have a minister, only themselves. And then they bought a lot where the church stood and they put up a tent and they had—</scene><scene id="18" in="00:04:49.28" out="00:05:22.06">Monique | Tent revivals. There you go.
Glenn | Meetings- Yeah, tent revivals. And the ladies and the young women, girls, my wife and a friend of ours, they would sew where it was ripped, where the wind would rip it. And they kept it going through the summer, you know. And then they moved that church in and made that their building.</scene><scene id="19" in="00:05:22.07" out="00:05:26.08">Monique | Hm. Interesting.
Glenn | That’s the first building.</scene><scene id="20" in="00:05:26.09" out="00:05:45.10">Monique | Alright interesting. If I could have, this is the release form that I talked about. So I, if I could have one of you get this filled in with your name and address and phone number. so that you can get that, a signature on file for ya.</scene><scene id="21" in="00:05:45.11" out="00:05:59.02">Margaret | Why I don't I fill that in for you. I’ll just put your stuff, your name on there, ecetera. 
Glenn | Okay.</scene><scene id="22" in="00:05:59.03" out="00:06:02.17">&lt;speaker&gt; Rachel Fore &lt;/speake&gt;
Rachel | What name am I using to save them?</scene><scene id="23" in="00:06:02.18" out="00:06:27.12">Monique | Right, so you said your last name is Bell.,
Margaret |  B-E-L-L.
Monique | Yeah so we’ll do Bell. So bell_1. 
Rachel | bell_1. And v at the end as well because, verso. 
Monique | Yes.. So, let’s go sequential and well do this as bell_0001</scene><scene id="24" in="00:06:27.13" out="00:06:43.15">Margaret |  It’s 705.
Glenn | Hamilton. 705 Hamilton avenue
Margaret | I know Hamilton
Monique | church and I think the one you’re doing now is. Oh wait, that’s the second church. So then this would be three. You don't have to name them until...Oh no you’ve already been saving them.</scene><scene id="25" in="00:06:43.16" out="00:07:08.15">Rachel | No, I’ve just been scanning them.
Monique | Okay. great.</scene><scene id="26" in="00:07:08.16" out="00:07:32.11">Monique | So if I understand what you said, before this building was physically in this location there was a tent there. So he was doing, Edward Wright was coming and doing tent revivals here at the same time he was going to the post office in Gilman and doing it there?
Glenn | Well yeah but it wasn’t just him. It was other Evangelists.</scene><scene id="27" in="00:07:32.12" out="00:07:49.29">Monique | Oh, coming to the tent. Okay. Okay. 
Glenn | Yeah. And one of them was Jack Hamilton and one of them was Ruby Pleatcher and her husband which would be Jim Miller’s sister that used to be the councilman.</scene><scene id="28" in="00:07:50.00" out="00:08:13.05">Monique | Huh Okay.
Glenn | And that’s how it started. 
Margaret | You can put your email there if you want to.
Monique | Yeah, if you've got email that would be great. Now, once these are—</scene><scene id="29" in="00:08:13.06" out="00:08:29.25">Glenn | I don’t have email. 
Margaret | I have it in here but I don’t know if you’d use it. 
Monique | You don’t have to have an email. So It’s just something—
Glenn | well right now I’m out of business. And I’ve got this laptop that’s giving me all kinds of problems.</scene><scene id="30" in="00:08:29.26" out="00:08:39.07">Monique | So one thing that’s nice about having these added to this collection then is that anybody will be able to get in and view them. 
Glenn | Right.
Margaret | Yes. Yes.</scene><scene id="31" in="00:08:39.08" out="00:08:59.06">Monique | Once they’re… this is the first step in the process but then eventually there will be somebody else who gets them up on the website. But once that’s done we can send an email to one of you if you wanted to email, so then you would know. Then  you could let other people that, who might be interested know that they can go there.</scene><scene id="32" in="00:08:59.07" out="00:09:10.00">Margaret | Should I put my email?
Monique | If you’d like to. And you can just put a note over the top of your name. That will help me remember that you’re not Glen. [laughs]
Margaret | Yes.</scene><scene id="33" in="00:09:10.01" out="00:09:29.13">Glenn | How this got started. My sister-in-law, she’s the only one let in the family of my wife. My wife passed two years ago. But my sister-in-law, she’s a, on a computer, she’s a computer wiz. 
Monique | Okay.</scene><scene id="34" in="00:09:29.14" out="00:09:55.16">Glenn | But anyway, she left Grinnell at an earyly age. She really didn’t know the history. Well she got on, looking up Grinnell and she read about the cyclone and the fire, and the early history of Grinnell she didn’t know anything about. And she got to go through the churches because she was in the church and she noticed there wasn’t anything in</scene><scene id="35" in="00:09:55.17" out="00:10:10.12">Monique | Right. Yeah, no, this is…
Glenn | there about the old church. And she wanted to know if I had any pictures or anything. 
Monique | Sure, sure. 
Glenn | And I said well yes I do. And she wanted me to get on this website.</scene><scene id="36" in="00:10:10.13" out="00:10:23.16">Monique | That’ great. I’m glad she did. I’m glad she did. Okay. Okay. I want to make sure I get the road right. So these were on Broad Street? Right? Okay. Now.
Glenn | Yeah. 619 Broad Street.</scene><scene id="37" in="00:10:23.17" out="00:10:32.27">Monique | 619 Broad Street.
Glenn | And I lived close there, under the water tower. 
Monique | Yeah?
Margaret | We were 629 Broad.
Monique | Okay.</scene><scene id="38" in="00:10:32.28" out="00:11:02.05">Glenn | So I knew everything that was going on at that time. 
[laughs]
Margaret | Sign your name here please Bud.
Glenn | I say everything but, most everything.</scene><scene id="39" in="00:11:02.06" out="00:11:21.17">Monique | And there weren’t…were there people? Yeah, okay. Do you know any of the people in this picture? 
Glenn | Yeah. 
Monique | Oh, you do? That’s very exciting.
Glenn | Yeah but how do you write the names down and get it, what line they’re in, about.</scene><scene id="40" in="00:11:21.18" out="00:11:39.20">Monique | Well that’s true. We can try. 
Glenn |  That’s alright with me. 
Monique | Because there’s a lot of people here. You know, we could do, if you know. Yeah, we could do if you know, yeah backrow front row. Even if you don’t know everybody sometimes if.</scene><scene id="41" in="00:11:39.21" out="00:11:56.08">Glenn | Or you could put UK, unknown.
Monique | Right, right. There’s not You’re right, they’re not in very nice neat rows but they are…
Glenn | But I know a lot of people in there. 
Monique | Yeah. You wanna…Let me,</scene><scene id="42" in="00:11:56.09" out="00:12:12.05">Glenn | Get that other picture…
Monique | Do you want to pull that one up and he can look at that. Can you see well enough? I’ve got a magnifying glass.
Glenn | That would help.
Margaret | That would be great.</scene><scene id="43" in="00:12:12.06" out="00:12:58.05">Monique | It’s not a great one, but it might help a little bit. It’s plastic. 
Glenn | Oh, yeah that helps. Well, up against the top of the steps, the doors, wall, the first one is Anna Figland. On the left. I’m going from left to right.
Monique | Anna Figland? 
Margaret | That’s F-I-G-L-A-N-D. And it was A-N-N-A was her first name.</scene><scene id="44" in="00:12:58.06" out="00:13:15.01">Monique | Okay. With the hat.
Glenn | Yes. 
Monique | All the women have hats. Is she the one with the light hat or dark hat?
Glenn | Yes, the one on the left, the dark hat.</scene><scene id="45" in="00:13:15.02" out="00:13:26.04">Monique | The dark hat. 
Bell, Then I think that’s Theodore Olsen. 
Monique | Standing next to her?</scene><scene id="46" in="00:13:26.05" out="00:14:26.10">Glenn |  Uh-huh. And then next to him would be Elizabeth Olsen which we called her, well that would be his wife. She would be a sister to Mrs. Figland.  That man leaning back, I don’t know for sure who he is. The one in the middle of the second top row I believe is Ray Holland.</scene><scene id="47" in="00:14:26.11" out="00:14:32.22">Monique | Holding the little boy?
Glenn | Holding the little boy.
Monique | Holland?
Glenn | Yes.</scene><scene id="48" in="00:14:32.23" out="00:14:58.26">Margaret | H-O-L-L-A-N-D.
Glenn | I don’t know who that lady is on the right. So you go down to the next row. 
Monique | Okay.
Glenn | And that’s Mrs. Belcher.</scene><scene id="49" in="00:14:58.27" out="00:15:28.00">Monique | In the back corner?
Glenn | Yeah. The next one is Clara Davenport. And I know that lady, what’s her name. Oh, I can’t think of what her name is.</scene><scene id="50" in="00:15:28.01" out="00:15:35.19">Monique | Do you want, we can make it bigger on the computer. Would that help? let’s see it
Glenn | Yeah.
Monique | Oh lets see.</scene><scene id="51" in="00:15:35.20" out="00:15:50.23">Margaret | Oh my this just gets better and better. You just keep thinking...more and more things.
Monique | Thre you go, that’s right. Why don’t you just scooch that over here Rachel.
Glenn | Oh yeah, that’s a lot. 
Margaret | Maybe you should get over here hon?</scene><scene id="52" in="00:15:50.24" out="00:16:12.21">Margaret | Let me hold stuff for you so that you can use your hands. I think you should have this chair bud,
Monique | You want to try that? just make sure it doesn't slide out from under you. That's those wheeled chairs.
Margaret | It's okay, I'm right behind you.
Monique | There's arms on it.
Margaret | We're good.</scene><scene id="53" in="00:16:12.22" out="00:16:23.10">Glenn | There. Oh yeah. 
Monique | There you go. Alright. 
Glenn | Oh yeah, that's much better. 
Monique | So I've got Mrs. Belcher.
Glenn | Yes.</scene><scene id="54" in="00:16:23.11" out="00:16:45.13">Monique | And Clara Davenport. 
Glenn | And this is the lady I know but I can't think of her name. This is Mrs Graham. 
Monique | Okay. 
Margaret | Here's that.
Glenn | I don't really need this Margaret, I mean.</scene><scene id="55" in="00:16:45.14" out="00:16:51.14">Monique | Yeah. We're making it bigger. 
Margaret | I know, I know. 
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | Okay. Point one out and I'll...</scene><scene id="56" in="00:16:51.15" out="00:16:58.21">Monique | Okay. Should we-
Glenn | That's Mary Wright.
Margaret | His mother-in-law.
Glenn | That's my mother-in-law 
Margaret | Eventually</scene><scene id="57" in="00:16:58.22" out="00:16:51.22">Monique | Alright.You said Mary Wright.
Glenn | Yes. 
Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | Viola Schooley.
Margaret | V-I-O-L-A</scene><scene id="58" in="00:16:51.23" out="00:17:25.17">Monique | Schooley?
Margaret | S-C-H-O-O-L-E-Y
Monique | Okay. So then here?
Glenn | Bessie McGrew.</scene><scene id="59" in="00:17:25.18" out="00:17:37.19">Monique | McGrew?
Margaret | M-C-G-R-E-W. Was that it? Yeah, I think so.
Glenn | Yeah.
Monique | Bessie McGrew...here?</scene><scene id="60" in="00:17:37.20" out="00:18:00.11">Glenn | Mrs. Holland. Another- it's a different Holland than the first one I told you.
Monique | Mrs Holland. And these folks are a little hidden back here.
Glenn | Well that's Della Woods next to her. 
Monique | And...?
Glenn | That's Fred Taylor.</scene><scene id="61" in="00:18:00.12" out="00:18:10.04">Margaret | Oh yeah.
Monique | You have got quite the memory Sir. [laughs]
Glenn | Yeah, it's going way back, a long time ago. 
Monique | Yeah.</scene><scene id="62" in="00:18:10.05" out="00:18:34.26">Monique | So Fred Taylor and... we can't see but just those guys eyes'. I'll be really impressed if you come up with names for them.
Glenn | Well I think that's my father-in-law there. Edward Wright.
Margaret | Yeah that's it.
Glenn | That's his eyes.
Margaret | That's his hair too.</scene><scene id="63" in="00:18:34.27" out="00:18:50.19">Glenn | Yeah. But that guy there, his mouth is closed or covered, I can't tell. 
Margaret | That short man?
Monique | Yeah and then there's- this fellow, just poking his nose up. [laughs]
Margaret | Yeah. He wants to be in the picture.</scene><scene id="64" in="00:18:50.20" out="00:19:00.23">Glenn | Well-
Margaret | No. There's Ed.
Glenn | Oh that's Ed. Yeah.
Margaret | This is isn't Ed.
Glenn | No, that's not Ed. That's Ed there.</scene><scene id="65" in="00:19:00.24" out="00:19:16.23">Glenn | Yeah. We got that wrong. 
Monique | Alright, well we'll so-
Glenn | Those two I don't know right now. Right now.
Monique | Okay. So we'll put a couple of question marksin there.</scene><scene id="66" in="00:19:16.24" out="00:19:43.01">Glenn | That's Austin and Henry Olson. That one- this is Austin and that's Henry. 
Monique | Okay. Olson? [mumbling] Austin Olson and Henry Olson.</scene><scene id="67" in="00:19:43.02" out="00:20:03.24">Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | That's my father-in-law, Edward Wright. 
[background chatter]
Monique | So then? Let's see, we kinda got off a little because the rows weren't so good.</scene><scene id="68" in="00:20:03.25" out="00:20:41.08">Monique | Let's see. Let's go, um, do you know the children's names?
Glenn | Well I think they're Holland boys.
Monique | Okay. We'll call that one front row. And you think those are Holland boys you said?
Glenn | I think so.</scene><scene id="69" in="00:20:41.09" out="00:20:50.23">Monique | And then the lady then here?
Glenn | We had 3 different families from Hollands and then.
Monique | Well that got a little confusing. So this lady? 
Glenn | That's Arelna Fleener.</scene><scene id="70" in="00:20:50.24" out="00:21:02.04">Monique | Arlena, O-R-L-E-N-A?
Margaret | A-R-L-E-N-A I think, does that sound right bud?
Monique | Fleener?
Margaret | And the F-L-E-E-N-E-R.</scene><scene id="71" in="00:21:02.05" out="00:21:11.20">Monique | I know that name, Fleener okay. 
Glenn | And then she's got that little boy. 
Monique | Yeah.
Glenn | And is he in a wheelchair? Or something?</scene><scene id="72" in="00:21:11.21" out="00:21:34.07">Monique | No, I don't think so.
Glenn | 'Cause, there was a-they had that boy that was- I don't know if he was in wheelchair but he-
Monique | I don't, no, he's not at that point.</scene><scene id="73" in="00:21:34.08" out="00:21:54.26">Glenn | Well that's a Holland boy there.
Monique | Yeah. So, let's- So we've covered pretty much these people. Lets with this lady here.
Glenn | Harper.
Monique | Harper. Okay.</scene><scene id="74" in="00:21:54.27" out="00:22:06.05">Glenn | And I said her name the other day. I don't remember, I told you.
Monique | Mrs. Harper.
Margaret | Mrs. Harper.
Glenn | Yeah, it was Mrs. Harper.
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="75" in="00:22:06.06" out="00:22:33.15">Monique | And...? Yeah cause we went- we did those gentleman back there, so, any of these kids or this lady here?
Glenn | Well this is Raymond Davenport. And that's Buela Spules.</scene><scene id="76" in="00:22:33.16" out="00:22:59.06">Monique | This lady here?
Glenn | I can't- Do you know here Margie? I can't- offhand I can't
Margaret | uh-uh. It's a young woman.
Monique | Yeah.</scene><scene id="77" in="00:22:59.07" out="00:23:10.15">Monique | So if we come over here, how about these folks? Oh no you gave me those names already I think.
Glenn | Well I didn't give you that lady's name.
Monique | Oh that's right, we were doing the guys. So what's...?</scene><scene id="78" in="00:23:10.16" out="00:23:34.13">Glenn | Well this here is Klowyk, Nelson Klowyk's wife. 
Margaret | Mrs Nelson Klo-I can't spell that name. 
Glenn | Well I didn't know her name. It starts with a K, Klowyk. 
Margaret | W-Y-K on the end?</scene><scene id="79" in="00:23:34.14" out="00:24:05.28">Glenn | Yeah. Yeah. And her mother was the one up on the porch, and he name was Graham. 
Monique | Okay. 
Margaret | I think that's Mrs. [indistinguishable]
Glenn | Now, I told you that lady was Buela Spuss. But that's Buela Spuss here. This lady here, I know who she is now, she's the mother of- used to be the insurance man in town.</scene><scene id="80" in="00:24:05.29" out="00:24:36.19">Glenn | He was in Richard's class at school. Well I know who she is, it will come to me. So, anyway.
Monique | So lets just- I don't know if I'm going to be able to  have them in any order anyways 'cause I'm getting confused as to which rows once we get over here. So I'm going to list the names that we know and we'll go from there.</scene><scene id="81" in="00:24:36.20" out="00:24:48.02">Monique | So, I think, I think- have we given these names?
Glenn | No, this is Buela Spuss. That's Ed Wright. 
Monique | Right, I've got that-
Glenn | That's Helen Bordiard</scene><scene id="82" in="00:24:48.03" out="00:24:59.08">Monique | Bordiard?
Glenn | Yes. 
Monique | Alright. 
Glenn | This is Herb Wyss don't you think Margaret?
Margaret | Oh it might be.</scene><scene id="83" in="00:24:59.09" out="00:25:06.10">Monique | Herb?
Margaret | H-E-R-B.
Monique | Wheech?
Glenn | Wyss: W-Y-S-S.
Margaret | Yeah.</scene><scene id="84" in="00:25:06.11" out="00:25:17.24">Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | And this is his wife Beulah Wyss.
Monique | Beulah: B-E-U?
Margaret | B-E-U-L-A-H I believe yes.</scene><scene id="85" in="00:25:17.25" out="00:25:30.28">Glenn | And there's a hidden man back there.
Monique | Yes. [laughs]
Glenn | This is T.W. Stark and he was the pastor. 
Margaret | That one time.
Monique | T.W. Stark. Alright.</scene><scene id="86" in="00:25:30.29" out="00:25:47.24">Glenn | And he was at Grinnell twice. That will be coming up. But he was the pastor, the first pastor. I think.  
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | And then...
Monique | Lets see if there's any more. Oh there are!
Margaret | Oh my! This is never going to end.</scene><scene id="87" in="00:25:47.25" out="00:25:52.26">Monique | There's more! Look at that! Alright.
Margaret | Look at that! Oh my.
Monique | Got any more names in there?
Glenn | There's my wife.</scene><scene id="88" in="00:25:52.27" out="00:25:58.05">Monique | Oh!
Glenn | Floss Bell.
Margaret | Yes, there's Flossy.
Monique | Florence Bell, alright.</scene><scene id="89" in="00:25:58.06" out="00:26:09.10">Margaret | Also known as Flossy.
Glenn | Look at the pigtails.
Margaret | She had very long braids didn't she. 
Glenn | We were married 65 years.
Monique | That's wonderful.</scene><scene id="90" in="00:26:09.11" out="00:26:27.26">Glenn | And that's when I- Well we were brother and sister for a long time. You know, I just lived at their house.
Monique | Yeah. Just grew up together. Isn't that sweet. 
Glenn | And this is Carmen Wyss. This is the daughter of these other Wysses.
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="91" in="00:26:27.27" out="00:26:47.26">Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | And who is that Margaret?
Margaret | I don't know. That's really a strange- a stranger to me. I don't know [laughs]
Monique | I'm sure it was just a stranger passing by [laughs]</scene><scene id="92" in="00:26:47.27" out="00:27:10.14">Glenn | There is one of those Holland boys. Another brother. 
Monique | A lot of Hollands huh?
Glenn | And there is old Jessie Holland. There is Raymond Wright.</scene><scene id="93" in="00:27:10.15" out="00:27:34.10">[mumbling]
Margaret | Maybe ought to finish over here before you go back to the left, but. 
Monique | Yeah.</scene><scene id="94" in="00:27:34.11" out="00:27:40.14">Margaret | You did Jessie Holland.
Glenn | Yeah. And I don't know-
Margaret | And is that Driscoll?
Glenn | No. No.
Margaret | That's not him.</scene><scene id="95" in="00:27:40.15" out="00:27:52.08">Glenn | There is George. That's George right there. George Driscoll.
Margaret | Okay. Okay. 
Glenn | That's George.
Margaret | I don't know who that man is.</scene><scene id="96" in="00:27:52.09" out="00:28:11.14">Glenn | Some of these tall heads I don't know.
Margaret | I think I was just about to be born. In that year.
Monique | Alright. Well...
Glenn | Well now this is Bobby Keith Stark. He was the preacher's son.</scene><scene id="97" in="00:28:11.15" out="00:28:29.16">Glenn | And here is Raymond Wright. 
Margaret | He looks really blonde in that picture. 
Glenn | He was in that growth state that your son is.
Margaret | Uh-huh.
Glenn | And he never did [indistinguishable]</scene><scene id="98" in="00:28:29.17" out="00:28:50.19">Glenn | This is Olan Teterman.
Margaret | That's right, he was really really slight wasn't he. Yeah.
Glenn | And I just, I couldn't put the name on some of these.
Monique | Yeah sure. Well that's a lot of names. So that's pretty darn good. That's very good.</scene><scene id="99" in="00:28:50.20" out="00:29:00.09">Glenn | And I might have misquoted.
Monique | And that's-
Margaret | That's not Ross down there in the left is it? In the corner?
Glenn | This one?</scene><scene id="100" in="00:29:00.10" out="00:29:05.02">Margaret | Uh-huh.
Glenn | I bet it could be. 
Monique | Ross?
Margaret | Wyss.</scene><scene id="101" in="00:29:05.03" out="00:29:12.21">Glenn | He's in the picture.
Margaret | Because Carmen is that age. I mean she's-
Glenn | See there's Carmen, right there. 
Margaret | Yeah that's his sister.</scene><scene id="102" in="00:29:12.22" out="00:29:21.07">Glenn | And I think that's Clayton Teterman. Don't you.
Margaret | Uh-huh.
Glenn | 'Cause he's up there with Ar- Yeah that's Clayton right there.
Margaret | Yeah. That is.</scene><scene id="103" in="00:29:21.08" out="00:29:31.21">Glenn | Now, would that be Sally Lunn-
Margaret | Beverly
Glenn | Beverly?
Margaret | Maybe.</scene><scene id="104" in="00:29:31.22" out="00:29:45.18">Margaret | I don't know. It would be Beverly because she and Ross were pretty much the same age.
Glenn | Well that could be Beverly.
Monique | Alright.
Margaret | And Sally was younger.</scene><scene id="105" in="00:29:45.19" out="00:29:56.26">Margaret | Moving on.
Monique | So I think- Lets call it good on that one. And-
Glenn | Oh you've got all those done. 
Monique | Yeah. So, I want to let her have the computer back so that she can scan these other ones while I jot down some notes.</scene><scene id="106" in="00:29:56.27" out="00:30:31.09">[mumbling] 
Monique | Okay. So, I wrote some stuff down about this one. So we're done with that one. This is the one that we were just looking at.</scene><scene id="107" in="00:30:31.10" out="00:30:47.22">Monique | So that one we're down with. 
[mumbling][movement]
Monique | That was the 30s. Trying to get all my paperwork straight here.</scene><scene id="108" in="00:30:47.23" out="00:31:16.09">Margaret | You bet, that's a lot to track. Let me move this hun so that you have a little more toe room. There you go, now you can move around.
Monique | Wrong papers, I'll be right back.
Margaret | Okay.</scene><scene id="109" in="00:31:16.10" out="00:31:46.13">Monique | So then this was the third building on that site?
Glenn | Yeah.
[mumbling]</scene><scene id="110" in="00:31:46.14" out="00:32:08.12">Monique | So this was built-
[phone rings]
Margaret | Excuse me. Oh I have to take this. I'll-
Monique | That's fine. 
[phone conversation]</scene><scene id="111" in="00:32:08.13" out="00:32:19.21">Monique | Lets see... Bud and Flossy. 
Glenn | That's me.
Monique | Oh, you were married in this church in '47. Okay. 
Glenn | Well, somebody put '47, we were married in '48.</scene><scene id="112" in="00:32:19.22" out="00:32:31.13">Monique | Oh. Okay. 
Glenn | So change that 7 to 8. 
Monique | Alright. I'll you do the writing on your picture but we'll make a note of that. Okay?</scene><scene id="113" in="00:32:31.14" out="00:32:43.24">Monique | And then... So you’re not sure when this picture was taken.
Glenn | Yeah. Yeah. I am. 
Monique | You are? Alright.
Glenn | When the picture was taken but you’re talking about when the church was built.</scene><scene id="114" in="00:32:43.25" out="00:33:16.26">Monique | Well tell me what you know about—
Glenn | ‘Cause it changed over time. 
Monique | Right. So this picture was taken in—
Glenn | Well, when you get to where the church was first charted it gives a list of the pastors, when they came and when they left. And this church was built when Reverend C.B. Bell came after Stark. And I don’t know where that list is at. Did she give you that list?</scene><scene id="115" in="00:33:16.27" out="00:33:46.08">Monique | Is that what was on the phone? 
Glenn | I think so. I think so.
Rachel | So, it was emailed to you and she asked for 3 copies.
Monique | Okay. I'll go get it. I'll go get that printed out. Okay.</scene><scene id="116" in="00:33:46.09" out="00:34:02.05">Glenn | Do you work everyday?
Rachel | I come in three days a week and scan photos and stuff. Yeah.
Glenn | Well that's nice to know how to do that.
Rachel | Yeah, I'm learning as I go. [laughs]</scene><scene id="117" in="00:34:02.06" out="00:34:28.24">Glenn | Well this information, I'm just about the last one that I know would have any. I mean they've all passed away, you know.
Rachel | Yeah.
Glenn | And, well, there might be a few but I'll say they're incapacitated. And so this information ought to be handed to somebody else, like, the historical society.
Rachel | Yeah.</scene><scene id="118" in="00:34:28.25" out="00:34:50.18">Glenn | It's a good deal.
Monique | Alright. Here are the list of the pastors.
Glenn | Okay. Now.
[mumbling]
Glenn | See this came from the district office in Des Moines.</scene><scene id="119" in="00:34:50.19" out="00:35:14.16">Glenn | And they don’t have it just right. See, there’s T.W. Stark up here at the Glad Tidings. He was here twice. 
Monique | Ah. But they've only got him there in '57.
Glenn | But he was here before Clarence Bell was here, 'cause we just looked at his picture. 
Monique | Yeah.</scene><scene id="120" in="00:35:14.17" out="00:35:45.06">Glenn | And they don’t have him down. But he came, Bell came after Stark so Stark was here until ’40 I suppose, ‘Cause Clarence Bell took over. And what I’m saying, is there any information here?</scene><scene id="121" in="00:35:45.07" out="00:36:00.09">Monique | That is the extent of what she had. So, that's all of it. 
Glenn | Well, she's got an email or something that tells.
Monique | Was there more than one email that needed to forwarded?
Rachel | No, I don't think so.</scene><scene id="122" in="00:36:00.10" out="00:36:18.25">Monique | I think- we can check with her when she comes back. So, this building- So tell me about this building, this brick building. The one you were married in you think was built—
Glenn | In 1940. I’ll say that’s when it was built. It might have been ’41.</scene><scene id="123" in="00:36:18.26" out="00:35:53.10">Monique | Sure. Approximately 1940. 
Glenn | Because his wife died and he left in ’44. So it had to be built while Clarence Bell was here. And I remember helping on it. And he was the one that overseen the construction.
Monique | Okay.</scene><scene id="124" in="00:35:53.11" out="00:37:03.01">Monique | Alright. And there’s no people in that one. And this picture was taken at a later date?
Glenn | Yes because, you see these balusters on here? They wasn’t built when the church was built. They reinforced that later. 
Monique | Yeah. Okay. Alright.</scene><scene id="125" in="00:37:03.02" out="00:37:26.06">Glenn | And it had a round roof. Well then, if you notice they had a fire. My sister-in-law was married in November 5th, 1950 and the church burned about a week later. So they had to gut it. And they took this round roof off and made a flat roof.</scene><scene id="126" in="00:37:26.07" out="00:37:53.12">Monique | Okay. So it burned in 1950 but they were able to repair it.
Glenn | Yeah.
Monique |  So it was repaired with a flat roof.  And then, did that stand until they built—
Glenn | The new church.</scene><scene id="127" in="00:37:53.13" out="00:38:14.05">Monique | The one that was the last building there.
Glenn | Yeah, they built a church on the side. Between here and that house and then they built an educational wing on the back and that would have been done when Reeves was here. And that gives the dates that he was here.</scene><scene id="128" in="00:38:14.06" out="00:38:33.10">Monique | So in the ‘60s?
Glenn | He was here from ‘67 to ‘88. He was here quite a long time. 
Monique | So probably in the Seventies this building was taken down to put up the other one? 
Glenn | They didn’t take it down. They just added on to it.</scene><scene id="129" in="00:38:33.11" out="00:39:01.08">Monique | Oh really?
Glenn | It wasn’t taken down until, Mayflower just took it down. 
Monique | Right. Okay. 
Glenn | So while we’re talking about this, the church was incorporated in ’34 in September.</scene><scene id="130" in="00:39:01.09" out="00:39:21.20">Glenn | And the church opened December 4th, ’34. And then it closed in 2009. But what I’m trying to tell you is that T.W. Stark who was the pastor from then until Bell came.</scene><scene id="131" in="00:39:21.21" out="00:39:37.22">Monique | Oh, so he was the founding pastor. Really for the first ten years or so if Bell didn’t come until forty. So he for the first six years.
Glenn | He was from ’34-’40. About six years. Five or six years.</scene><scene id="132" in="00:39:37.23" out="00:39:44.05">Monique | Stark was. And then he came back in the fifties. 
Glenn | Yeah. To open the Glad Tidings.</scene><scene id="133" in="00:39:44.06" out="00:40:14.10">Monique | Okay.
[mumbling about scanning]</scene><scene id="134" in="00:40:14.11" out="00:40:38.01">Monique | Okay. So this photograph we think was taken in what would have been the late forties because it still has the round roof. 
Glenn | Well I would say until 1950 because then they made a flat roof, ‘cause it burnt down.</scene><scene id="135" in="00:40:38.02" out="00:40:47.11">Monique | Right, so this picture was before it burned so it must have been in the forties.
Glenn | Well, we were married in ’48 and we was married in this church.</scene><scene id="136" in="00:40:47.12" out="00:41:12.25">Monique | Okay, so it must have been, yeah. What you’re saying is that this round roof went away in fifty. So this picture is maybe about 1948. We’ll guess 1948. That’s what it looked like when you got married. It says right here that the pastor is D.E. Skieles. Is that pastor that married you?</scene><scene id="137" in="00:41:12.26" out="00:41:30.09">Glenn | No. He was there, but he went on vacation. There's Skieles. But he went on vacation. So Clarence Bell came back and married us. 
Monique | [laughs] Well that worked out alright.
Glenn | Yeah,worked out.</scene><scene id="138" in="00:41:30.10" out="00:41:51.03">Monique | Okay. Wow. Alright. Some good stories here. So we've got this one. Tell me about this picture. Is that in a parade? 
Glenn | Oh where did that come from?
Monique | It was in there with them.
Glenn | Oh here it is on the back, first parade of the Assembly of God.</scene><scene id="139" in="00:41:51.04" out="00:42:08.10">Monique | Well there you go. 
Glenn | And they got 1923-24, well that’s incorrect. 
Monique | Oh alright.
Rachel | There might be a correction further down
Glenn | Oh, it says, “I believe this was taken in the area of ’33-35. Bob Smith”.</scene><scene id="140" in="00:42:08.11" out="00:42:21.16">Monique | Oh so that's all written out. 
Glenn | And the Bluebird Cafe [mumbled]. I remember that in the bus depot. Percy Doc Mercy. Haven't heard that name in a long time. [mumbles]</scene><scene id="141" in="00:42:21.17" out="00:42:40.23">Glenn | Well what they got done, I gave this to Bob Smith and he's wrote.
Monique | He added those notes? Okay. So that's got some good information on the back already. So we've got that scanned.
Rachel | Yeah.</scene><scene id="142" in="00:42:40.24" out="00:42:55.14">Glenn | But the Assembly of God's church wasn't founded in 24 to 30. It didn't start till early 30s.
Monique | That's why they corrected it. [laughs]
Glenn | Oh they did correct it.
Monique | Yep. It's corrected yeah. 
Glenn | Okay.</scene><scene id="143" in="00:42:55.15" out="00:43:10.04">Monique | They said that it wasn't taken until the 30s.
Rachel | And that one's 005
Monique | Okay.</scene><scene id="144" in="00:43:10.05" out="00:43:24.27">Glenn | We used to have center parking uptown. 
Monique | I've seen pictures of that. Yeah.
Glenn | And I wondered if it showed that on there.
Monique | Yeah. I found a picture that- on Broad street. Where they had the cars angle park in the middle.</scene><scene id="145" in="00:43:24.28" out="00:43:57.25">Glenn | Yeah. Well that's the history. They had a parade didn't they?
Monique | Yeah they did. Alright, so there is that one. And this one has got all of the people- This has got the names of the people on it. So we won't need to write those names down. We can pull that off of there.</scene><scene id="146" in="00:43:57.26" out="00:44:22.12">Glenn | I think that was maybe Dedication Day.
Monique | Ah. Yep. Okay. So this is the one now... I need to go get another piece of paper. And then we're going to have you see if you can give us some of those names</scene><scene id="147" in="00:44:22.13" out="00:44:52.26">[pause]
[scanning noise]</scene><scene id="148" in="00:44:52.27" out="00:45:26.05">Glenn | I'd better wait till she gets here. I wanted to fill this in when T.W. Stark came to Glad Tidings. He came when the church was affiliated in '51 here. They got that down but they don’t have him as the pastor. But he was the pastor, there’s his name and it started in ’51 but it isn’t up here.</scene><scene id="149" in="00:45:26.06" out="00:45:43.19">Monique | Alright. Well I’m going to guess I get to keep one copy for our records and that she wanted these other ones. So I’ll make a note on our copy. That you think he started in 1951? 
Glenn | I know he did. I was there.</scene><scene id="150" in="00:45:43.20" out="00:46:03.09">Monique | Alright. Okay. So, lets- What do you know about this picture? Does it say on the back? 1950s. Okay.
Glenn | Well it was 1951 or 1952 because the church didn’t start until 1951.</scene><scene id="151" in="00:46:03.10" out="00:46:22.25">Monique | Okay. She's going to make it nice and big for you and you can tell us names that you remember again. Alright?
Glenn | Alright. 
Rachel | and then if you want it bigger you just...
Monique | So lets start in the front row
Glenn | Okay.</scene><scene id="152" in="00:46:22.26" out="00:46:43.07">Monique | We'll start in the front row over here okay?
Glenn | Well those two little boys I think are Schooley boys. Margaret isn't here to correct my memory.
Monique | Schooley boys?
Glenn | Yeah.</scene><scene id="153" in="00:46:43.08" out="00:46:52.29">Monique | Alright.
Glenn | And the first lady is Margaret Wright.
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="154" in="00:46:53.00" out="00:47:27.05">Glenn | The next lady is Beverly Lunn. And then Ross Wyss. Edward B. Wright. Herb Wyss. T. W. Stark and his wife, Sister Stark, Bernice.</scene><scene id="155" in="00:47:27.06" out="00:47:48.24">Glenn | And Viola Schooley. 
Monique | Viola Schooley?
Glenn | Yes. Can I get closer?
Monique | Yeah, we can get it a little closer. I think it will be alright if we unplug it. It's probably got enough battery power.</scene><scene id="156" in="00:47:48.25" out="00:48:02.19">Glenn | Well it-
Monique | Do you need it bigger?
Glenn | Well it dimmed a little when she unplugged it.
Monique | Yeah. You can either have it closer or you can have it brighter. Was it better when it was brighter?
Glenn | Yeah.</scene><scene id="157" in="00:48:02.20" out="00:48:18.14">Monique | She just needs another inch for her cord there. We don't have very good power options on this table. 
Glenn | I'll-
Monique | Here, lets see if we can make it bigger too. Should we make it bigger?
Glenn | There. Yeah.</scene><scene id="158" in="00:48:18.15" out="00:48:31.04">Glenn | Oh yeah. That's better. 
Monique | So where were we at. The last name I have down is-
Glenn | Is Viola Schooley.
Monique | Viola Schooley. Yeah.</scene><scene id="159" in="00:48:31.05" out="00:49:02.21">Glenn | And that's the lady I'm to figure out. 
[background noise]
Glenn | I think it's Mrs Raymond Wright.</scene><scene id="160" in="00:49:02.22" out="00:49:19.19">Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | Wynetta Teterman. 
Monique | Wynetta ?
Glenn | Teterman
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="161" in="00:49:19.20" out="00:49:53.10">Glenn | Virgil Wright. I don't know those kids right now.
Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | Margaret ain't here. And then that's Lavine Kline.
Monique | Kline with a C or with a K, do you know?
Glenn | K.</scene><scene id="162" in="00:49:53.11" out="00:50:01.12">Monique | With a K. Okay. 
Glenn | Now do you want to go back to the left.
Monique | Yes, lets go back to the left.</scene><scene id="163" in="00:50:01.13" out="00:50:20.13">Glenn | Okay. 
Monique | So second row.
Glenn | Okay. And that's Portia Wright. And that's dark, too dark for me to tell who that boy is.
Monique | Okay.</scene><scene id="164" in="00:50:20.14" out="00:50:33.25">Glenn | And there's a little girl there and I don't know who offhand. 
Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | I think that might be Steven Wright.</scene><scene id="165" in="00:50:33.26" out="00:51:08.03">Glenn | And there's the little Pinkerton girl. That might be a Childers girl. And then Denise Gally.</scene><scene id="166" in="00:51:08.04" out="00:51:20.18">Monique | Gally?
Glenn | Gally: G-A-L-L-Y
Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | And there's another Gally boy.</scene><scene id="167" in="00:51:20.19" out="00:51:40.11">Glenn | Margaret's not here to tell me which one. 
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | And, there's another boy there but I can't make out who he is. And another boy. I don't know.
Monique | That's alright.</scene><scene id="168" in="00:51:40.12" out="00:52:02.07">Glenn | And this boy I don't know. And the next child I don't know 'cause I can't see the whole face. 
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | I think that's Danny Paul there. Danny Paul Wright. 
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="169" in="00:52:02.08" out="00:52:19.09">Glenn | And then Bobby Kline. 
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | And then this here, boy, that I didn't mention, cause I thought he was in another line, but that's Jean Teterman.</scene><scene id="170" in="00:52:19.10" out="00:52:30.18">Monique | Alright.
Glenn | And then we've got to go to the left again.
Monique | Yep. So this is like the third row.</scene><scene id="171" in="00:52:30.19" out="00:53:00.02">Glenn | I'm trying to figure who that boy is. This is a Lunn boy. L-U-N-N. And then Leon Wright. And then someone's holding a baby up in the air. 
Monique | Okay.</scene><scene id="172" in="00:53:00.03" out="00:53:30.04">Glenn | And there's a Childer's boy. And then Mary Wright. And then the other, I think this here is Daryl Wyss. W-Y-S-S. This must be a Bitner girl.</scene><scene id="173" in="00:53:30.05" out="00:54:00.17">Glenn | And then another Bitner, the father. Can't think of his name. 
Monique | You're doing great. You've got a lot of names in that head, so you're doing fabulous.
Glenn | And that's Sandra Lunn, Sandy Lunn. I think we called her Sandy Lunn.</scene><scene id="174" in="00:54:00.18" out="00:54:38.03">Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | And here's a Pinkerton girl and what was her name? She's a Pinkerton. Oh my goodness. Okay, we're talking about her.</scene><scene id="175" in="00:54:38.04" out="00:54:49.18">Glenn | I want to say Lindley but that's her sister. 
Monique | Okay. Well I'll put question mark Pinkerton. Okay?
Glenn | Mrs. Gussy 
Monique | Gussy?</scene><scene id="176" in="00:54:49.19" out="00:54:58.10">Glenn | Uh-huh. Crocket. Gussy Crocket. 
Monique | Gussy Crocket?
Glenn | Yeah. Mrs. Gussy Crocket. 
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="177" in="00:54:58.11" out="00:55:25.18">Glenn | And then I don't know whether to go down or up. This is Mrs. Bisson holding a child. A child I don't know. 
Monique | Mrs. Bisson with child, alright.
Glenn | And then this lady on the end, that's the daughter of this Crocket and right now I can't think of her first name.</scene><scene id="178" in="00:55:25.19" out="00:55:48.14">Monique | Crocket, alright. Okay, should we got back and do the 4th row then?
Glenn | Alright. Okay. 
Monique | So, let's see, 1,2,3 so I think we're here.
Glenn | That's Karen Smith.</scene><scene id="179" in="00:55:48.15" out="00:56:05.25">Glenn | Oh this is a Bisson girl. 
Monique | Next to Karen?
Glenn | Uh-huh. And I can't think of her name.</scene><scene id="180" in="00:56:05.26" out="00:56:19.07">Monique | Okay. Who is next to her?
Glenn | Well, I don't know what line we're on.
[laughs]
Glenn | And that's Eddie Wright, my brother-in-law.</scene><scene id="181" in="00:56:19.08" out="00:56:41.21">Monique | Alright.
Glenn | Holding one of his kids. 
Monique | Ed Wright with child. Alright.
Glenn | Okay. I've figured out who this lady was. 'Cause I thought this lady here was the one that was down here. But this is one of Fred Kline. And this is his wife.</scene><scene id="182" in="00:56:41.22" out="00:56:48.19">Glenn | That's Raymond Wright and his wife. 
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | And I can't think of her name right now. 
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="183" in="00:56:48.20" out="00:57:00.10">Glenn | That's-
Monique | Well, lets see, because we were here. So have we done this lady?
Glenn | That's my mother-in-law Mary Wright.
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="184" in="00:57:00.11" out="00:57:19.04">Glenn | This is Arthur Schoolie with one of his kids, probably Wayne, cause he was the youngest. And those kids down on the first row that I couldn't think of that would be- he had five boys. 
Monique | Okay. So Arthur Schoolie with Wayne. Alright.</scene><scene id="185" in="00:57:19.05" out="00:57:35.25">Glenn | And that's Mrs. Beulah Wyss. Oh that Bitner that I couldn't think of his name, is Donald. And there he is in, that's Donald. 
Monique | Alright. [laughs]
Glenn | That's Donald.
Monique | Donald Wyss.</scene><scene id="186" in="00:57:35.26" out="00:57:54.14">Glenn | And that's Mrs Beulah Wyss.
Monique | Yep, with got Beulah Wyss.
Glenn | Okay. And this is Carmen Wyss, well she's Carmen Schoolie. She's the mother of those 5 boys.</scene><scene id="187" in="00:57:54.15" out="00:58:11.14">Monique | Alright.
Glenn | And then it's Beulah Sparks, Sylvia Sparks.
Monique | Sylvia?
Glenn | Uh-huh.</scene><scene id="188" in="00:58:11.15" out="00:58:13.11">Monique | You're catching all this right?
Rachel | Yeah.</scene><scene id="189" in="00:58:13.12" out="00:58:31.13">Glenn | Arlie Binegar
Monique | Arlie? A-R- Arlie Binegar?
Glenn | Uh-huh. And then that's my grandma Cooper.
Monique | Grandma Cooper. Did she have a first name.</scene><scene id="190" in="00:58:31.14" out="00:58:54.04">Glenn | Pauli. 
Monique | Pauli Cooper. Alright. 
Glenn | And then here's Elizabeth Olson, Gracie Beeler, and here's my sister Margaret, who is sitting here with me.
Monique | You're in there? Which one are you?</scene><scene id="191" in="00:58:54.05" out="00:59:08.21">Glenn | (Margaret) I'm not in there, I was working. 
Monique | Oh alright. Alright. So Margaret Beeler, Bell, no?
Glenn | She was married to Ross Wyss.
Monique | Margaret Wyss.</scene><scene id="192" in="00:59:08.22" out="00:59:15.27">Glenn | At one time. 
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | So then we've got to go back to here.
Monique | Now we've got to back, that's right.</scene><scene id="193" in="00:59:15.28" out="00:59:22.27">Glenn | And that man's name-
Monique | So that's the fifth row. Okay. Wow. Alright. 
Rachel | This just never ends [laughs]</scene><scene id="194" in="00:59:22.28" out="00:59:45.23">Glenn | Ah I know him.
Monique | Yeah I can just see the wheels spinning in that brain: "what's his name?" [laughs]
Rachel | Wow. 
Glenn | I can't think of his name now</scene><scene id="195" in="00:59:45.24" out="00:59:59.02">Glenn | It's simple. 
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | And we already did these two. Now that's Swede Johnson.
Monique | Swede?</scene><scene id="196" in="00:59:59.03" out="01:00:09.06">Glenn | Yeah.
Monique | Swede Johnson. Alright.
Glenn | There's a kid peeking it's-
Monique | There is! Just a nose [laughs]</scene><scene id="197" in="01:00:09.07" out="01:00:31.16">Glenn | And that's Robert Tede and probably one of his girls.
Monique | Robert Tede. Okay. 
Glenn | And that lady I can't see enough of her to.
Monique | Well</scene><scene id="198" in="01:00:31.17" out="01:00:50.12">[recorder gets moved]
Monique | Want me to make it bigger? I can make it bigger on the computer.
Glenn | Okay. 
Monique | Kinda hard to make out, a lot of that face is blocked.</scene><scene id="199" in="01:00:50.13" out="01:01:04.10">Glenn | Well his wife would be in there. But that don't look like his wife. Well anyway, I can't tell you who that is right now. 
Monique | Alright.
Glenn | This is Ruby Tede.
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="200" in="01:01:04.11" out="01:01:18.12">Glenn | This is Beeler.
Monique | Beeler? Mr. Beeler?
Glenn | Yeah. 
Monique | Okay.</scene><scene id="201" in="01:01:18.13" out="01:01:24.03">Glenn | And that's Wilson.
Monique | Mr. Wilson
Glenn | George Wilson
Monique | George Wilson.</scene><scene id="202" in="01:01:24.04" out="01:01:53.24">Glenn | And this is his wife. I think her name was Emily. That was it, Emily.
Monique | Emily Wilson?
Glenn | Uh-huh. And this is Helen Wilson. George and Helen go together. And that man up there...</scene><scene id="203" in="01:01:53.25" out="01:02:08.19">Monique | Want me to make him bigger?
Glenn | Uh, I can't tell you-
Monique | He's pretty- it's pretty dark up there. Doesn't get much better.</scene><scene id="204" in="01:02:08.20" out="01:03:07.02">Glenn | Well, this is Elizabeth Olson. They called her Liz. This is Mrs. Lunns, can't think of her first name. That's my uncle Guy Cooper.
Monique | Guy?
Glenn | Uh-huh. This is Bobby Keith Stark, preacher's son. Well wait just a minute, is that Bobby or Donnie?</scene><scene id="205" in="01:03:07.03" out="01:03:16.19">Glenn | I don't know if that's Bobby or Donnie. 
Monique | I'll put Bobby or Donnie Stark. Stark?
Glenn | Yeah.
Monique | Alright.</scene><scene id="206" in="01:03:16.20" out="01:03:41.08">Glenn | And Clayton Tederman. And this man up here at the top, he's the last man, I do not know who he is. That man.
Monique | Alright. Couple of, maybe they were just visitors that day. [laughs] 
Glenn | Could have been.
Monique | Alright, well that- very well done. That's a lot of names. That's wonderful.</scene><scene id="207" in="01:03:41.09" out="01:03:52.02">Rachel | Wow. 
Glenn | But me and my wife weren't there that day.
Monique | Darn it. [laughs] But you knew everybody else who was. 
Glenn | Yeah. Pretty much.</scene><scene id="208" in="01:03:52.03" out="01:04:28.04">Monique | Alright, so, got it? Okay. So, and that one was Bell_0004 if it was the church one.
[movement]</scene><scene id="209" in="01:04:28.05" out="01:04:49.10">Glenn | She had another picture in this but. 
Monique | This one? With these?
Glenn | No, not that one. But that's alright. It was done at the other church. A youth group. With about 15 names, nice picture.</scene><scene id="210" in="01:04:49.11" out="01:05:01.24">Monique | I think this is actually the same picture. Or a very close-
Rachel | I think it was taken the same day, just two.
Monique | Yeah.</scene><scene id="211" in="01:05:01.25" out="01:05:31.01">Glenn | I might be in these pictures. I've never looked at these. 
Monique | You haven't looked at those?
Glenn | Well, for years.
[laughs]</scene><scene id="212" in="01:05:31.02" out="01:06:14.07">[pause]</scene><scene id="213" in="01:06:14.08" out="01:06:41.11">Glenn | Well we can add that one later. If we want to.
Monique | Yeah. Yeah. We're gonna run out of time here so we might- If you've got, I know she said she had another book with some possible things so. She's in talking on the phone. She had some kind of a phone call she had to take. So she's in- sitting in our break room [laughs]</scene><scene id="214" in="01:06:41.12" out="01:06:58.13">Monique | So, do you- are these, these are kids here it looks like. Mostly, well are there adults in the back?
Glenn | There's a few adults.
Monique | 1956. So are those names you know? Do we want to try and put names on that as well?</scene><scene id="215" in="01:06:58.14" out="01:07:13.04">Glenn | No, I think we'll just... Have people get on that site they can look at the other pictures.
Monique | Alright. 
Rachel | And figure it out.
[laughs]</scene><scene id="216" in="01:07:13.05" out="01:07:36.25">Glenn | And see if they're in there. 
Rachel | How do you want me to save the booklet? Because I have this as 008 and this page, would that be 009 or 008b?
Monique | Why don't you save the two of them together as a PDF. Because as a PDF, since it's type written we'll OCR it and then it can be searchable.</scene><scene id="217" in="01:07:36.26" out="01:07:58.00">Glenn | I typed that myself. And that's why I saved it. It's just a history thing.
Monique | Sure. Sure. Okay. So, 
Rachel | So I'll save them both
Glenn | But that's the way things have changed</scene><scene id="218" in="01:07:58.01" out="01:08:16.09">Glenn | Because you had to memory graph that. That's all out the door
Monique | Yeah. That's right. Yeah, that old purple ink. 
Glenn | Yeah.
Rachel | Oh that's not an option.</scene><scene id="219" in="01:08:16.10" out="01:08:44.13">Monique | Okay. Alright. So let me just make sure we've got what we need for the stuff we've scanned today. We've got- We'll get those things put back in your book. Got the parade, the old post office building, the first church</scene><scene id="220" in="01:08:44.14" out="01:08:56.19">Monique | The brick church, all those members, we've got this
Rachel | Should I still save it here or should I put it in Bell photos?
Monique | Bell photos, yep, they're with Bell photos.</scene><scene id="221" in="01:08:56.20" out="01:09:29.13">Monique | So here are those items, so that you can get them back. And then, lets ahead and scan this and put it in the same file just so that we've got everything together in digital form. 
Rachel | Okay.</scene><scene id="222" in="01:09:29.14" out="01:09:55.04">Glenn | These are some of the old preachers. And that's the preacher Clarence Bell. Clarence Bell and his wife. That's my uncle and that's my in-laws. Oh this, this is my father-in-law and I'd like to put that in the scrapbook.</scene><scene id="223" in="01:09:55.05" out="01:10:06.09">Monique | With what we're doing you mean?
Glenn | No, it wouldn't be with the church.
Monique | But you'd like to add it to the digital archives?
Glenn | Yeah.
Monique | We would love to have that. Yeah.</scene><scene id="224" in="01:10:06.10" out="01:10:22.02">Glenn | Well here is a big picture of it. And I could give it to you and-
Monique | Well, would you be able to come back another day?
Glenn | Yeah! I live in Grinnell.
Monique | Yeah we would love to have you come back and-</scene><scene id="225" in="01:10:22.03" out="01:10:31.06">Glenn | But I'm just showing you.
Monique | And I know she also talked about, was it your father that was police chief or?
Glenn | Yeah.
Monique | Yeah?</scene><scene id="226" in="01:10:31.07" out="01:10:42.28">Glenn | Oh I've got his books here if you want to look at them or scan them.
Monique | Yeah.
Glenn | Right here.
Monique | We won't do the newsclippings, but if you've got photographs and stuff we'd love to have them.</scene><scene id="227" in="01:10:42.29" out="01:11:04.25">Glenn | I don't have any photographs [mumbled] in there I don't think but you can see what there is. And then you'll know what we're talking about. 
Monique | Oh I'm upside down.
Glenn | I think that's my sister's scrapbook.</scene><scene id="228" in="01:11:04.26" out="01:11:21.14">Monique | Oh yeah, the one with the clippings.
Glenn | With the war effort. And she was-
Monique | So those, yeah, we wouldn't 
Glenn | She never had any children and they made me the geneologist. To keep her stuff.</scene><scene id="229" in="01:11:21.15" out="01:11:30.00">Monique | Oh I see. 
Glenn | But it's very interesting about the boys. 
Monique | Yeah.
Glenn | The war stories and stuff.</scene><scene id="230" in="01:11:30.01" out="01:11:43.18">Monique | Hmm I like this, even though that's Newton. 
Glenn | Well I went to sail and that picture of my sister worked there at that company. 
Monique | Oh yeah?
Glenn | And I just picked up the photo and brought it home.</scene><scene id="231" in="01:11:43.19" out="01:12:09.25">Monique | There you go. [mumbled] business cards. But these are-
Rachel | Invitations or tickets?
Monique | Colorado</scene><scene id="232" in="01:12:09.26" out="01:12:40.02">Monique | Yeah, these are new- Oh wait here we've got some stuff. Oh Kansas, must have been places they've visited. So probably, I don't see anything in here that we would add 'cause they're not- it's either news clippings or things from places other than this area.</scene><scene id="233" in="01:12:40.03" out="01:12:55.02">Monique | Looks like it's got scrapbooks from places they visited in Colorado and-
Glenn | Yeah, but it's got all those Grinnell boys that-
Monique | Yeah, we can't do the news clippings for this project, so we're gonna- we're doing newspaper stuff a different way.
Glenn | Okay.</scene><scene id="234" in="01:12:55.03" out="01:13:14.07">Monique | So, but this must be the scrapbook with the police stuff. She said a lot of it is newspapers, but see now here is the police stuff. 
Glenn | My mother kept that for my dad. She's the one that did it.</scene><scene id="235" in="01:13:14.08" out="01:13:24.00">Monique | I see that.
Glenn | He was police chief for like 10 years in the 40s.
Monique | Oh yeah? Oh yeah see here we go. 
Rachel | Wow.</scene><scene id="236" in="01:13:24.01" out="01:13:45.29">Monique | That's Belldale [mumbled] From other places, places that he went. Where he went to school. Yeah.
Margaret | This is from Beth: "squeeze, squeeze Uncle Bud for me"
Glenn | How are things going?
Margaret | Oh it's rough but</scene><scene id="237" in="01:13:46.00" out="01:14:02.20">Glenn | It's rough?
Margaret | But it's going. 
Monique | See there's his graduation card. There are a few things in here I think we would like to scan. Picture of him from- now is Fred Rupe, was that your-?</scene><scene id="238" in="01:14:02.21" out="01:14:10.28">Glenn | No he was a policeman. 
Margaret | No he was a policeman.
Monique | Oh okay, so this is-
Glenn | My dad was Glenn Bell. Same name I got.</scene><scene id="239" in="01:14:10.29" out="01:14:34.06">Monique | Alright. Cause yeah, see there's some picture here. But this is not all Grinnell. This is other places where he was a police officer?
Glenn | No that's all-
Monique | It's all Grinnell. I'm just parousing quickly so I wanted to make sure.</scene><scene id="240" in="01:14:34.07" out="01:14:44.21">Glenn | No. He was police chief for 10 years.
Monique | Okay. So all these pictures of him in his police garb, that's him as a policeman here in Grinnell?
Glenn | Yeah.
Margaret | Yeah.</scene><scene id="241" in="01:14:44.22" out="01:14:59.24">Monique | So you know, a lot of them move around now, they stay in one town for a couple years.
Glenn | No, this is all Grinnell stuff. 
Monique | Wow. So everycase he was involved in was in the paper. She's got a clipping.
Margaret | I think she got it.</scene><scene id="242" in="01:14:59.25" out="01:15:06.10">Rachel | Wow. 
Monique | Ooh look. A FBI fingerprint ID thing. That's pretty cool. That'd be neat to have.</scene><scene id="243" in="01:15:06.11" out="01:15:38.13">Monique | So we're about out of time today that we've got. So I was saying that if he'd be interested in bringing it back we could set another time when we could maybe do a few more things. 
[mumbles]
Glenn | Well you know I've got them and if you get the newspaper thing ironed out...</scene><scene id="244" in="01:15:38.14" out="01:15:45.11">Monique | Right. Well what we're hoping, newspapers, we actually have all the old newspapers on microfilm.
Glenn | Oh I see.</scene><scene id="245" in="01:15:45.12" out="01:16:05.20">Monique | And they have equipment now, we don't have it but you can send it away where they digitize the old newspapers and they do it so that you can actually go in and search and find anything in it. So they make a giant database so you could enter you father's name and pull all these articles up that way.</scene><scene id="246" in="01:16:05.21" out="01:16:21.22">Monique | So that's why we're not- plus there's copyright issues with newspapers that are just easier to avoid. 
Glenn | Now this sheet [indistinguishable] is my wife. A beauty shot 50, 60, 70 years ago. 
Monique | Oh yeah? How about that.</scene><scene id="247" in="01:16:21.23" out="01:16:30.01">Glenn | Oh here is that picture I was looking for. From the old church.
Monique | Okay. 
Rachel | do you want me to scan that?
Monique | Yeah, lets do that one real quick</scene><scene id="248" in="01:16:30.02" out="01:16:39.11">Glenn | I didn't know if we'd brought it or not. 
Monique | We will do that one real quick and we will get those names. 
Glenn | Yeah.
Monique | There aren't too many of them so I think we can do those quick.</scene><scene id="249" in="01:16:39.12" out="01:16:53.08">Monique | Here's copies of that document.
Margaret | Oh thank you so much.
Monique | So is 2 enough for you or did you want one more? And then I'll keep one with these items that we've got. 
Margaret | Yes. I know, I have two extras. This is the listings of the pastors of the church.</scene><scene id="250" in="01:16:53.09" out="01:17:02.08">Glenn | Yeah I know, I want one. 
Monique | And he's making- he was already correcting some of it. He said that they don't have all the dates right so [laughs]
Margaret | Okay.</scene><scene id="251" in="01:17:02.09" out="01:17:32.22">Glenn | Well, Stark was there two times. He's in the first building photos and is not listed in there. 
[mumbling]
[movement]
Margaret | I'll put them in this sack</scene><scene id="252" in="01:17:32.23" out="01:17:50.13">Glenn | But I was wondering, this would be about her?
Monique | Yeah. And I would love to have it, but I can't do it since it's a newspaper clipping and because of copyright rules. So for this project I can't do newspaper clippings.
Glenn | Alright</scene><scene id="253" in="01:17:50.14" out="01:18:12.20">Glenn | Well somebody told me, like Jess Rutera, his gastation, they brought a picture in, was that a picture or was that the newspaper?
Monique | It was a photograph that somebody found in a scrapbook. Yeah. So it was a photograph, not a newspaper clipping.</scene><scene id="254" in="01:18:12.21" out="01:18:31.07">Monique | So...
Rachel | But the newspaper clippings will be available
Monique | Yeah. The newspaper clippings will eventually be, we hope, available online, just not as part of this particular project. It's just one of the limitations that we have with what we're doing, so.</scene><scene id="255" in="01:18:31.08" out="01:18:54.14">Margaret | Now, if I get an email from you, it's going to be from the library, Drake library, or from the historical ta-da-ta-da. 
Monique | When you see it?
Margaret | Right.
Monique | So, my name is Monique, it will probably come from monique@grinnelliowa.gov. It would probably come directly from me.</scene><scene id="256" in="01:18:54.15" out="01:19:15.00">Margaret | Cause you know, sometimes you don't even open things cause you don't know.
Monique | Right. So have you got one more group of names in you if we look at the pictures of these folks?
Margaret | Oh yeah.
[recorder movement]</scene><scene id="257" in="01:19:15.01" out="01:19:24.13">Monique | Can you name those folks?
Glenn | Yeah. This is my wife Florence Bell. 
Monique | Okay. 
Glenn | This is Anna Allen.
Margaret | Thank you dear.</scene><scene id="258" in="01:19:24.14" out="01:19:31.04">Rachel: You're welcome [mumbled]
Glenn | This is Doris Bell.
Monique | Okay. Hold on. Florence Bell and Anna Allen.
Glenn | Uh-huh</scene><scene id="259" in="01:19:31.05" out="01:19:49.28">Monique | Alright.
Glenn | Doris Bell, Fay Allen, Carmen Wyss, Pauline Dobbs, Ray Allen.
Margaret | Slow down.</scene><scene id="260" in="01:19:49.29" out="01:19:56.27">Monique | So now we're in row 2?
Glenn | Yeah. Emil Gerard.
Monique | Oop. Go back to first guy in row 2.</scene><scene id="261" in="01:19:56.28" out="01:20:06.01">Glenn | Ray Allen
Monique | Now they're all coming to you real quick. You're going faster than I can write [laughs].
Margaret | This is more recent.</scene><scene id="262" in="01:20:06.02" out="01:20:11.12">Glenn | Emil Gerard.
Monique | Emil?
Margaret | E-M-I-L
Monique | Gerard. Okay.</scene><scene id="263" in="01:20:11.13" out="01:20:22.18">Glenn | Now is he in that line or another line?
Monique | Hmm, Yeah. I'd come down here. 
Glenn | Helen Burchard.
Monique | Burchard?
Glenn | Uh-huh.</scene><scene id="264" in="01:20:22.19" out="01:20:37.08">Glenn | Is that Harriet Cooper? Yeah. Another Cooper- different Cooper. Harriet. And that's-
Margaret | Margaret Gally.
Glenn | Margaret Gally.</scene><scene id="265" in="01:20:37.09" out="01:20:47.14">Monique | Okay. Third row. 
Glenn | And this is-
Margaret | You. That's him. 
Glenn | Glen Bell, I was known as Bud.</scene><scene id="266" in="01:20:47.15" out="01:20:47.18">Monique | [laughs]. You were known as Bud, I'll put that in parenthesis. Bud Bell. Alright.
Margaret | He's still Bud.
Glenn | I got to get my glasses going. Oh that's Lucille deGreve wasn't it?</scene><scene id="267" in="01:20:47.19" out="01:21:08.16">Margaret | Yes.
Monique | Degreve? D-E-G-R-E-V-E
Margaret | But are you skipping a row?
Monique | No, and then yeah lets go to her.</scene><scene id="268" in="01:21:08.17" out="01:21:36.26">Glenn | Mary Clayton, before she was married. Bulla Sparks, Bintner.
Margaret | Ah, Bintner,  Don was the husband. 
Glenn | No, that was his sister.</scene><scene id="269" in="01:21:36.27" out="01:21:53.12">Margaret | Oh...
Glenn | She's got a funny name. 
Margaret | We could say Mrs. or Miss somebody
Monique | Yeah well. Yep.</scene><scene id="270" in="01:21:53.13" out="01:22:10.05">Glenn | Klotwyk. Can't think of her first name.
Monique | White is the last name.
Margaret | Klotwyk.
Glenn | K- Klot, K-L-O-T-W-Y-K or W-K-Y or whatever it is.</scene><scene id="271" in="01:22:10.06" out="01:22:14.26">Margaret | Yeah.
Monique | Oh, it's the last name.
Margaret | Yes. 
Monique | Okay. So, somebody Klotwyk. Alright.</scene><scene id="272" in="01:22:14.27" out="01:22:21.24">Margaret | That's Mary Allen, or Mary, yeah, isn't it?
Glenn | Is that who that is?
Margaret | I think so.
Glenn | Mary Allen?</scene><scene id="273" in="01:22:21.25" out="01:22:30.22">Monique | Mary Allen, alright. And then the two guys in the back?
Margaret | Don't you think that's her?
Glenn | Nelson Klotwyk and Don Bintner.</scene><scene id="274" in="01:22:30.23" out="01:22:49.13">Monique | Nelson Klotwyk and Don Bintner. Alright.
Glenn | They were brother and sister. I can't say her name, I'm all out.
Monique | You've done good.</scene><scene id="275" in="01:22:49.14" out="01:22:57.26">Margaret | Lillian, Lillian is the wife. 
Glenn | That's the wife, but that ain't Lillian. 
Margaret | I know, but I'm getting there. 
Monique | [laughs]</scene><scene id="276" in="01:22:57.27" out="01:23:08.13">Margaret | Don't shut me out.
Monique | Well this has been wonderful. This has been wonderful. I'm so glad you came in, this is wonderful.
Glenn | Well I'm glad that my sister showed up cause I'd never get this done.</scene><scene id="277" in="01:23:08.14" out="01:23:22.04">Monique | Well, very good. Very good. So next time she comes to visit you can come back and bring in more things. 
Margaret | And bring these- what are we to bring next time?
Glenn | Well we can't bring these till she calls me.
Margaret | Okay.</scene><scene id="278" in="01:23:22.05" out="01:23:45.19">Monique | Well, yeah, the ones with newspaper clippings. The one that has the pictures of the, the one with the police officer pictures. Cause that has some photographs in it in addition to the newspaper clippings, so we'd like to have that one back.
Margaret | Yes. Okay.   
Monique | And then, you also had some other pictures from the church that you said were pictures of the pastors and some different things.</scene><scene id="279" in="01:23:45.20" out="01:23:54.21">Glenn | Oh I've got lots of pictures.
Margaret | He's got so many others. 
Glenn | This is for the church.
Monique | Okay. Alright. This is for the church so we've got the church stuff recorded.</scene><scene id="280" in="01:23:54.22" out="01:24:05.01">Margaret | This is good, we really appreciate.
Glenn | Now, how long will that take to get it on the?
Margaret | A month or 2 years, or?
Glenn | I just want to tell my sister-in-law in Colorado.</scene><scene id="281" in="01:24:05.02" out="01:24:21.16">Monique | Right. Right. Well, I will talk to the lady that does the next step tomorrow and see if she can bump it up on her list of priorities. I'll let her know we have some anxious folks waiting to see them online. 
Glenn | Okay. 
Margaret | After all these years we're suddenly "right now"</scene><scene id="282" in="01:24:21.17" out="01:24:30.01">Monique | No! That's great. This is exactly the kind of thing we were hoping for, so this is really wonderful. 
Glenn | Okay. 
Margaret | Oh good. 
Monique | This is great.
Margaret | That's good.</scene><scene id="283" in="01:24:30.02" out="01:24:46.19">Monique | And, I'm very, very impressied with you memory Sir. So, [laughs]
Margaret | You should ride down the street with him.
Monique | I bet.
Margaret | Because it's "Now, do you remember when that house was moved in and the Smith's lived on that side and the Brown's lived over here?"</scene><scene id="284" in="01:24:46.20" out="01:25:17.25">Monique | Well you know, another thing that we're doing as a part of this is sitting down and collecting those stories and turning on a tape recorder and letting you tell stories about the early days. So, well, I'm going to have Rachel here try to type out what you've told us today if it came through ok on the recorder. But if you were interested, we could set somebody up to come over and you could tell some other stories about growing up in Grinnell and-</scene><scene id="285" in="01:25:17.26" out="01:25:31.03">Glenn | Well I could if is she would get me going. 
Monique | [laughs]
Margaret | He's full of it. Because I'm very interested. A lot of people are just like "Well, lets- could you go a little faster, we need to get there". And I'm like "Oh really?" you know and-</scene><scene id="286" in="01:25:31.04" out="01:25:57.19">Monique | Yeah.
Margaret | "When was that?" and-
Glenn | Well we hadn't been- She came earlier last year. I have bouts of sickness. And she comes down and takes care of me. But, anyway, she likes to go for rides and we can just get in the car and go and, we start talking about where we hadn't been to the Blue Point.</scene><scene id="287" in="01:25:57.20" out="01:26:06.11">Glenn | Well that church that's on the Fairgrounds
Monique | Uh-huh.
Glenn | Well they moved it into town. That's the old lower Blue Point church.
Monique | Right.</scene><scene id="288" in="01:26:06.12" out="01:26:30.01">Glenn | Well we were going to go out where it used to be, because there's a cemetary there and we'd go visit the cemetary and we couldn't find the cemetary. 
Monique | hum
Glenn | And we spent two trips before we found the cemetary.
Margaret | Then I got my phone out and did Mapquest: "Oh there it is! Let's go for one more road and then we'll be there"</scene><scene id="289" in="01:26:30.02" out="01:26:33.05">Glenn | And they've got a lower cemetary and a-
Margaret | And a north, and a south, and a lower, and an upper or something like that.
Glenn | Which I didn't realise till we- 
Monique | There you go.</scene><scene id="290" in="01:26:33.06" out="01:26:49.06">Monique | Well very good.
Glenn | A lot of history there.
Margaret | So he is absolutely a historian.
Monique | Yeah? We'd love to have more of your memories captured, so.
Glenn | Well-</scene><scene id="291" in="01:26:49.07" out="01:27:01.07">Monique | She's got you the help to get out there?
Glenn | I'm too much.
Margaret | I've got your cane right here.
Monique | Alrighty.
Glenn | Now I've got to get motape here.</scene><scene id="292" in="01:27:01.08" out="01:27:12.29">Monique | Okay. And you can find the-
Margaret | Thanks ladies, very much appreciated. 
Monique | Well  thank you. Yes, very nice to meet you.
Margaret | And I imagine, are you volunteering Rachel or are you on the payroll?
Rachel | Yes.</scene></transcript>